Finding Aid for Theodore R. Schmale Papers.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Theodore R. Schmale Papers 1918-1961 1929-1961
Schmale, Theodore R., d. 1969
2 linear feet
85384 Aa2
Papers,1918-1961,of Theodore R. Schmale, pastor of Bethlehem Evangelical Church [now Bethlehem United Church of Christ]; includes manuscripts of sermons (partially in German); and autobiography,1895,of father-in-law, Johann H. Dinkmeier, describing life in Germany, his immigration to the United States, and his experiences as a teacher and Evangelical pastor. [original and typescript of translation]
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated. (donor 6553)
No further additions to the collection are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Theodore R. Schmale, son-in-law of German immigrant Johann H. Dinkmeier, received his A.B. degree from the University of Pittsburgh and B.D. from the Western Theological Seminary (Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania). He served for twenty years as pastor of St. Peter's Evangelical and Reformed Church in the same city before moving to Ann Arbor, where he served as the sixth pastor of the Bethlehem Evangelical Church (now Bethlehem United Church of Christ) from 1928 to 1951.
Theodore Schmale was also a member of the Board of Foreign Missions of the Evangelical Synod, made two trips to Honduras related to the mission work of his denomination (in 1938 and 1941), and served in other community positions. Among them, he was a Board Member of the Y.M.C.A., member of the Community Chest Board, and President of the Ann Arbor Ministerial Association.
During Schmale's pastorate at the Bethlehem Evangelical Church, a parish house was constructed, the interior of the sanctuary was renovated, church membership nearly doubled, the congregation's business office was improved, and the church program was enlarged to include the support of a Missionary in India. After his retirement, Pastor Schmale continued to preach German services. He died in Detroit on June 4, 1969.
The Papers of Theodore R. Schmale consist primarily of his manuscript sermons, most of them dating from 1929 to 1961. These sermons are arranged in three separate sections: chronologically, by topic, and by scripture reference. In addition, the collection contains a small quantity of biographical material on Theodore Schmale, an 1895 autobiography of Schmale's father-in-law, Johann Heinrich Dinkmeier, and an English translation from the autobiography's original German. Dinkmeier's autobiography describes life in Germany, his immigration to the United States, and his experiences as a teacher and Evangelical pastor.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Church history.; Bethlehem United Church of Christ (Ann Arbor, Mich.).; Clergy--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Michigan--Emigration and immigration.; German Americans--Michigan.; United Church of Christ--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Germany--Emigration and immigration.; Immigrants--Michigan.
Contributors:
Dinkmeier, Johann Heinrich, b. 1849
- Johann Heinrich Dinkmeier
  - Autobiography [in German] (Box 1)
  - Translation of autobiography (Box 1)
- Theodore R. Schmale
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
  - Sermons (Chronological)
    - undated (in German) (Box 1)
    - 1918 ?,1929-1940 (Box 1)
    - 1941-1945 (Box 1)
    - 1946-1950 (Box 1)
    - 1951-1952 (Box 1)
    - 1953 (Box 1)
    - 1954 (Box 1)
    - 1955 (Box 1)
    - 1956 (Box 1)
    - 1957 (Box 1)
    - 1958 (Box 1)
    - 1959-1961 (Box 1)
  - Sermons (Topical)
    - Christmas (Box 1)
    - Denominationalism (Box 1)
    - Easter and Lent (Box 1)
    - Fourth of July (Box 1)
    - Funerals (Box 1)
    - Labor Day (Box 1)
    - Lord's Prayer (Box 1)
    - Memorial Day (Box 1)
    - Missions (Box 1)
    - Mother's Day (Box 1)
    - Peace (Box 1)
    - Prejudice Prosperity (post World War II) (Box 1)
    - Special occasions (Box 1)
    - Thanksgiving (Box 1)
    - Washington's Birthday (Box 1)
    - World conditions (Box 1)
  - Sermons (by scripture reference)
    - New Testament
      - Matthew (Box 1)
      - Mark ;Luke (Box 1)
      - John (Box 1)
      - Acts (Box 1)
      - Romans (Box 1)
      - Corinthians; Galatians; Ephesians (Box 1)
      - Philippians; Colossians; Thessalonians (Box 1)
      - Timothy; Hebrews; James (Box 1)
      - Peter; Revelations (Box 1)
      - [In German] (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Old Testament (Box 2)
      - Genesis to Joshua (Box 2)
      - Judges to Solomon (Box 2)
      - Isaiah to Malachi (Box 2)
      - [In German] (Box 2)
  - Sermons (fragmentary) 15 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellanea (Box 2)
    (include church programs)